off the intro to all my like first 200
shows so no way oh my gosh isn't that
crazy we're gonna have some kitties
visiting us i hope you don't mind
kitties i love kitties they love people
pets hey everybody and welcome to chef
aj live i'm your host chef aj and this
is where i introduce you to amazing
people like you who are doing great
things in the world before i introduce
today's guest chef i want to let you
know you have 36 hours left to buy the
book and get the bonuses you have more
than 36 hours to buy the book but if you
want to get all the wonderful bonuses
that we created like the audio files for
free so you don't need to buy the book
on audible when it comes out which will
be very soon and a lot of bonus recipes
that were not in the book only because
we just didn't have time we had to get
the book out and my exclusive double
frosted vanilla carrot cake including a
video tutorial simply buy the book by
midnight on sunday october 18th email us
are you our your receipt to chef aj
bonus yahoo.com and we will get those
bonuses right to you without further ado
today's guest chef i met him during a
thing that i was doing for dr doug
graham who i'd love to have on the show
one day by the way but i'm booked to
march 22nd
and it's a show that he has for free on
sunday mornings at 9am called let's cook
raw if you want more information on that
i can tell you about it and i said to
everybody that was doing i said guys
want to come on the show he's the only
one that contacted me he seems like a
lot of fun his name is chris kendall and
he's going to be making chris's creamy
curry welcome chris it's so nice to see
you
so stoked to be on here thanks so much
for inviting us all i can't believe i'm
the only one here but jeez i want to
connect with you and with everyone here
who's watching today and watches all
your amazing content i feel blessed to
be here where are you where are you
broadcasting from
you know i'm broadcasting live from
saskatoon saskatchewan canada home of
the great white north and sweaters that
are also called bunny hugs
and you got a kitty on the counter we
love pets on this show we always have
kids on the counter here it's very cold
so i will distract myself by closing the
window when they come off their cat
balconies just you know this is the
walkway to their cat balcony so i can't
you know obstruct that yeah well i'd
love to know more about you how long
have you been a chef um why you why you
chose raw how long you've been being
tell us everything before you start the
recipe oh and somebody already knows you
gina says i love this chef
and diane says cool looking dude so you
got you got some admirers oh thank you
thank you
you know
it seems like it's been a lifetime but
it's been since about 2000 that i really
started changing my diet
before that i was a skateboarder looking
to be a professional and doing anything
but eating health food i was just
drinking and smoking and eating fast
food non-stop started falling apart and
saw a real need to change things up so i
found yoga which kind of led me to
literature that talks about healthier
eating and vegetarianism and karma and i
just really started taking it on the the
first big book i saw was fit for life
and that was now like over 12 20 years
ago and it completely changed my world
you know i started food combining i
started eating fruit for breakfast
slowly moving towards vegan it actually
took me about three and a half four
years to go vegan
so i've been vegan for 16 and a half
years now
oh 17 years now and
it was when i was when i went vegan i
was in school for holistic nutrition at
a school called canadian school of
natural nutrition csn
and you know before that i really wanted
to be a chef i always liked making food
i made food for all my friends but i
couldn't find a chefing school at that
time around 2004 that was a vegan
chefing school right so instead i went
to the nutrition and during nutrition
training i went to a vegan festival and
met dr doug graham just as you mentioned
and you know so that's over been 16
years ago i met doug and i went raw
overnight and the first five years of
being a raw foodist i just poured a ton
of time and energy into making tons of
different raw food dishes started
therawadvantage.com 11 years ago and
launched my first recipe book which was
meant to pretty wide acclaim and picked
up by the people at the woodstock fruit
festival and so i've been the head chef
at the woodstock fruit festival most of
the years of the last decade and became
known as a world-renowned raw food chef
because of that because they really
launched me into the big spotlight with
everyone else and
you know so
it's been now
16 years raw vegan and 17 and a half
vegan that's incredible well nicole says
chris also makes the best raw pizza on
the planet and i highly recommend his
recipe book that's pretty cool tell us a
little bit more about this raw this
woodstock fruit festival well the
woodstock fruit festival is the longest
running biggest raw food festival in the
world
like most festivals they took this last
summer off but the 10th anniversary will
be coming in 2021 it's in upstate new
york and
it's awesome you know it's like a raw
food party with over 600 people tons of
long-term raw food enthusiasts kindred
spirits coming together just to enjoy a
healthy raw food diet along with just
all the lifestyle factors that really
plus up your nutrition and your whole
healthy lifestyle
so you want raw so quickly you didn't
even have a transition of like being a
regular vegan or a junk food vegan you
kind of went right to raw
well kind of yes kind of no because you
know it was like a three and a half four
year transition from total junk food
like drink or smoker to a whole foods
high raw vegan and when i went vegan i
was already eating fruit for breakfast
and fruit for lunch i was just having
some cooked dinners that sometimes
included some animal products
and you know i went uh when i went vegan
it was about six months whereas
basically just
hi what do they call they call raw till
four typically now these days right so i
was i was basically wrong till four for
about six months then i met doug and
then it was just overnight right into
all wrong
that's amazing i did raw for a couple of
years and i think it's great you know
the biggest problem i had is i never
slept you have so much energy when you
don't eat cooked food it's like you just
never you don't need sleep
yeah you can bounce off the walls and
you know i really did notice myself that
for
you know a good like four to six months
i wasn't sleeping quite as well and
after that i started to sleep a lot
better and and these days i love sleep
like i try and get a good eight or nine
hours if i can but the more i exercise
the more i need of course and no i i
love it nothing compares for me and
that's what keeps me on the track i've
been 100 raw for i think the longest
stretch was about five six years and now
i'd say i'm like 99 wrong that's what
i've been most of the time
as with this recipe there is one thing
that is on the hazy ground and of course
i use some spices and stuff which are
questionably raw but i like to make up
the vast majority of my diet with 100
raw foods you don't find that where you
are you get too cold eating 100 raw
no you know i i did in the first year
year and a half and my feet would get
cold as my circulation improved but what
i found was after that period of time
and just getting used to a slightly
lower body temperature because most
people who are 100 raw they actually sit
about a degree cooler
and they usually are more well hydrated
really hydrated with high water content
foods so it they can feel a little
colder at first but after that initial
break-in period i felt totally normal
and you know if it was extra cold then
sometimes i might just get some extra
exercise or wear a little bit of extra
clothing or i like to make warm stuff
still you know some people think raw
food is just eat cold stuff or room
temperature stuff all the time but i
like to blend you know hot water with
dates and some carob or cacao
and make like a hot chocolate so i used
to actually work outside doing
construction in minus 40 weather as 100
raw foodist and i did fine i just
dressed appropriately and ate enough
calories to make sure i was really nice
and warm
that's great tell us about your tattoos
because we we know what every tattoo has
meaning
well i got a lot of different tattoos i
i can't even say
how many i don't know don't know the
count but i know i have over 90 hours of
tattoo work on my body
yeah so i'll show you the first one here
i'll get nice up and close and personal
got the banana mustache if you can see
it it's just banana mustache going on
and i i got the vegan one so i'm i'm in
there for life that one's up and down
back and forth i got love and faith on
my wrist
and then i got
double dragons dragging up this arm and
then a dragon on my chest going down
this arm my entire back is a phoenix
with the uh chakra symbols going
anatomically correct on each chakra uh
we've got some chest pieces got a banana
down here oh and uh yeah that's the one
we want to see you want to see
i'm just kidding you know this is this
is uh children might be i'm just i'm
sorry i'm sorry
i do have videos of some of my tattoos
so if you check out my uh youtube
channel
what's your couple different videos
what's your name advantage right
advantage great yeah we'll link to
everything in the show notes well i love
curry so i love that you're making this
recipe
yeah you know i think i was uh
you know i i love curry too i think i
was an indian in the last life you know
i i absolutely love it i could have this
all the time and truthfully
this recipe i'm going to share today is
my third version of this the first time
i made it was called cocoa butter
veggies and that was
a decade ago and it was my favorite
recipe and about two years ago i kind of
updated it and made the 2.0 which is i
think a little bit healthier and more
accessible and easier and cheaper to
make
and just recently i actually updated it
to version 3.0 so this is my this is
probably my most eaten raw recipe
for the last two years
wow
at least yeah
should we dive right in you guys want to
learn all about this the christmas
creamy curry you bet
all right awesome awesome well you know
the base of this recipe is just with
three simple ingredients and you know
this is kind of uh you know some rest
some ingredients that some raw foods
don't eat a lot of and that other people
like say dr greger really promotes
heavily what i've really found is some
of these ingredients if you start with a
little bit and slowly increase your
microbiome adjusts and you feel more
comfortable eating larger amounts and
digesting it easier i'm just bringing
that up because i know some raw foodists
that just eat fruit and greens and have
a hard time eating things like
cauliflower or mushrooms which i
absolutely love and can be really
delicious so
the main main components of this curry
is kind of like
a mix between aloo gobi if anyone's had
l gobi that used to be my all time
favorite and butter chicken but of
course without the butter or the chicken
originally i was going to call it no
butter no chicken
curry but that's not as you know it
doesn't roll off the tongue so smoothly
so
i want to let you know that this recipe
it does actually start the night before
and this is just one texture trick that
i really really like to use and can be
used on a ton of different vegetables
and i find makes a huge difference it
actually made it so that my raw curries
went from yeah i like them too like wow
i like this better than any cooked curry
no no word of a lie so it's going to
start the day before with cauliflower so
we're starting off with about three
quarters of a pound or 345 grams of
cauliflower
now that's fresh cauliflower right here
but what we did is i chopped it up into
nice little bite-sized pieces and i put
it in the freezer overnight now by
putting it in the freezer overnight
the water in it expands and ruptures the
cell walls so when you thaw it out it
softens it and it actually tastes and
appears to be cooked and it digests a
little bit easier too so it's kind of a
neat little process that i love to do so
here we have
that same amount of cauliflower that i
actually froze last night and i just let
it thaw on the counter
sometimes when i'm in a rush i'll just
thaw it under some warm water or
otherwise i might put it in my
dehydrator at a low temperature like 105
or 108 and just let it warm up over a
couple of hours but we'll start with
that we have the cauliflower we'll just
put it in this big bowl
you can see it's really nice and soft
and tender just breaks apart
most people wouldn't even realize that
it's not cooked which is kind of fun the
next ingredient yeah that's a cool
did you figure that technique out
yourself the freezing and the
yeah you know i mean i i can't say that
i own it because i'm sure people have
been freezing have discovered it but
i've never seen any chef or raw chef
promote it ever you know and i didn't
find it out by myself and it's kind of
fun because
certain ingredients like cauliflower or
broccoli or even brussels sprouts work
amazingly with it mushrooms soften up
and kind of get moist almost like
they're stewed uh onions when you freeze
them in thumb they almost seem like
they're sauteed
i've done other ones like asparagus
which is on the fence and cabbage i tell
you you you finely shred cabbage fries
and thought and it tastes like you just
you know steamed or boiled a whole bunch
of cabbage but there's more nutrition
intact because you're not losing it in
the water one question susan is asking
about raw mushrooms because i know
there's been some doctors that say that
mushrooms are one thing that shouldn't
be eaten raw
absolutely and you know that's a subject
that i've really looked deeply into
because i do eat a lot of mushrooms i
love them you know they're the only
foodborne source as a vegan foodborne
source of vitamin d
and when i looked into the study because
you know
very often in nutritional science we get
a study we get some information and
someone hears it and then they just
repeat it without even really looking
deeply into the study and i won't say
that i've read every study that's ever
been done but i've read multiple studies
that have been referenced by very
well-known doctors saying that we
shouldn't be eating raw mushrooms and
when you actually look at the science
what it shows is that those studies are
based on rats or mice given an isolate
of one compound found in mushrooms and
art is called argatine or not pronounced
right but agaritine
one compound in isolate form in the
quantities equivalent to a year's worth
of mushrooms in one day and then it was
found to be potentially carcinogenic or
trouble problematic right so
myself i know i'm not going to be eating
that much in an isolated form i'm eating
a whole food and we know that almost any
food has a has some kind of a compound
in it that if you isolate it and
put it in that huge of a quantity can
cause issues
mushrooms like most other foods that are
self-delimiting meaning
kitty
if you start eating them you stop
enjoying them far before any kind of a
toxic low to be reached you know it's
the same with like say spinach or any
other kind of really harder green it
could could actually have some compounds
at large quantities causing issues but
no one eats them in that quantity so i
myself am not concerned about mushrooms
at all
i usually actually like to put them in
the dehydrator like slice them up and
put the dehydrator for an hour or two
which does actually decrease the target
the argan team um also transport and
time since pix decreases the guarding
and heat does as well and that's why
some people say that you should cook it
but i've been eating a lot of raw
mushrooms over the years and i feel
amazing and all my tests and including
kidney and all those kind of tests show
really good results
so hopefully that helps that question a
bit great thank you so we have mushrooms
and we're going to do roughly the same
quantity of the three main ingredients
being the cauliflower and now the
mushrooms so with the mushrooms i have
12 regular sized cremini mushrooms
i will say that some mushrooms are
higher in that compound than others
cremini
button mushrooms portobello mushrooms
are typically the ones i use the most
i sometimes use shiitake and
occasionally use oyster although oyster
are kind of on that edge and i would say
too you know what if you are concerned
about it just lightly roast your
mushrooms or dehydrate them at a really
high temperature or even put them out in
the sunlight when it's nice and sunny
out because it's been shown that putting
mushrooms under a uvb light or under the
sun
increases the vitamin d content so much
that a handful can become a vitamin d
supplement so that's kind of a neat
little fact as well
but these ones i didn't put in the
dehydrator just to show that you don't
necessarily have to
i'm just cutting them up into quarters
by putting them on their back side and
then cutting them from the stem and down
into quarters if you like smaller chunks
you can cut them into uh
sixes or eights
but this is usually how i do it it's
kind of nice too when you put them in
the dehydrator for
an hour maybe two hours at around 1 15
118 they just shrink up a little bit
they get a little bit more kind of juicy
and firm
and
their flavor is just that much more
pronounced
another little trick with mushrooms as
well is you don't really want to wash
them but instead you can take a damp
paper towel and just kind of dab on them
and that way
they don't suck up the moisture from the
water but you can clean them off
so
there we go we have our mushrooms in
there
and the next ingredient
is one that i'm going to give a few
options for and for what i used here
today is the only real thing in here
besides some spices that isn't
technically a hundred percent raw
so that one here is actually some green
peas
so
these ones are frozen peas and frozen
vegetables are typically blanched which
means they're put under hot water or
boiling water for one to three minutes
to retain color and flavor
so these guys were just thawed out green
peas that i i took out this morning and
let it sit on the counter until they're
nice and thawed again sometimes i might
just run them under hot water or
otherwise put them in the dehydrator at
a low temperature for a while
if you can find fresh green peas which
everyone knows are really crunchy and
delicious you can use those fresh green
peas or you can use that same freezing
technique because if you freeze fresh
fresh potted peas they turn out really
soft and delicious and almost seem like
they're cooked another option instead of
peas you could sprout lentils you know i
love to sprout brown lentils green
lentils even red lentils if they're
whole and that makes an amazing addition
to this as well so this is about the
same weight or same quantity
we're looking at about a cup and a half
here of green peas and i'm just going to
pour that on over top of this so
in the big bowl we have the frozen
thought cauliflower the mushrooms which
i typically dehydrate and the peas
next we're going to get into the sauce
and that's the fun part right because
everyone knows it's all about the sauce
are you a sauce lover i love sauce
that's what that's the secret to
everything i think is sauce it really is
and you know i'm gonna just shamelessly
plug something real quick i got a really
fun dressings book but something else
that i'm really proud of is actually a
book called naturally raw some sauces
and the entire intention of that is to
turn you into a raw vegan
sauce chef it gives you all the tricks
and tips into making tons of different
types of sauces and
it just really can make the biggest
difference because
you can put good sauce in almost
anything and that meal is awesome but if
you don't know how to make a sauce then
you can feel like you're just eating
bland food all the time so that's
something that i really like to showcase
and share
but getting into this sauce it uses a
little trick that i use sometimes that
is different from the first two versions
and what that is is i'm starting off by
making a broth
so you might ask what is a raw food
broth a raw food broth is really just a
raw food juice so i'm just making some
juice and you can use any kind of root
vegetables or vegetables to make a juice
as the base of your sauce and that way
it just makes it a lot more rich and
smooth and creamy because my my first
one was actually made with coconut milk
second one was just made with water
blended with a bunch of stuff and then
this one utilizes some carrot juice so i
have about a pound of carrots or four to
five carrots here
and i'm just going to chop them up
roughly
for some different sauce recipes like a
thai
kind of a recipe i might make a broth
out of carrots and celery and some
lemongrass and that can be the base of a
nice curry sauce or even a nice thai
curry soup
right but this one
starts off with these carrots so i'm
just going to take this vitamix jug here
and put all the carrots in there now you
might be saying what i thought you're
making a juice why are you using the
vitamix
i'll be honest i'm a little lazy
i do have a juicer but i just find
blending it with the vitamix and then
putting it through a nut milk bag to be
actually easier and less clean up
it definitely
has a little less nutrition with the
oxidization depending upon the juicer
you would have but again i'm a little
lazy i just find it works really well
and really quick so
you know what i apologize i forgot one
thing i'm gonna have to run and get my
tamper cause go ahead i'll i'll
entertain everyone
all right do something so
how is everybody doing today
i'll just do a shameless plug because
i'm really happy the book is doing well
and i appreciate you guys support
the bonuses are really good i'm told
well yeah i've listened to the book on
tape it's even more fun than reading it
so that's why you want to get it now
because i know what's going to happen
like 1201 we're going to get all these
things please is it too late yeah it's
too late we had somebody on the first
book two years later send us the receipt
asking for the bonuses we won't have
them after so
let's get them now thank you very much
joyce says i hate cleaning the juicer
too what kind of juicer do you have i
have the champion juicer and i love
using it to make banana ice cream oh
nice yeah that's good i love banana ice
cream too you know i
i actually don't even know the name of
it but i know that it's like a knockoff
looks like one of the better kind of
omega or champion juicers uh it's a
central your central career goal uh slow
turning one that kind of crushes it
against the screen and it makes good
quality juice but geez it takes time to
clean up right so
that's why i end up using this one
instead
and a good nut milk bag is so versatile
you know you can really use it for a lot
of different things whether you're
making some like you know nut cheeses or
broths or juices anything like that so
so we'll just plug your ears guys i
apologize this vitamix has one thing
that i wish it was could improve on is
just being silent but it's pretty noisy
so
i'm just going to blend this up and i'm
going to really tamper it hard so it
becomes really into a nice mush mix
[Music]
i
so there we go
and all we got to do is have a nice bowl
already
and dump as much of this as you can
into the nut milk bag
sometimes it doesn't want to come out at
all
sometimes it does and i really don't
mind if there's a little bit of carrot
pulp left in the blender i just want to
get the absolute biggest quantity of
that out
there we go so that's not too bad
and then we'll just squish that
nice fresh sweet carrot juice and that's
one of the things that this really adds
to the recipe
is one of course lots of awesome
nutrition from the carrots high in
vitamin a and nice and sweet and natural
sweetness
but also food combines a little bit
better i am a proponent of food
combining but i don't always do a tea
and my
version before this actually utilized
water with dates as kind of the main
sweetener whereas this the carrot juice
is going to be a little bit better in
strict food combining principles than
you have so
there we go so we squeeze that out
and we'll add this back to the blender
and hope that we have around one cup
wow so you didn't they uh there's a
question if you used any water you
didn't with the carrot right
none at all so that's it's actually
awesome that's really exactly one cup
which is about one pound of carrots and
you know depending on the carrot sizes
that could be anywhere between
between uh you know two to six or seven
carrots right
so that's going to be the base of our
sauce so we have the beautiful carrot
juice in there
to that we'll actually add our seeds
so
i like to mix it up and some people
don't like to mix different seeds but i
find when it's blended all together it
works really well and there's different
nutrients in each of these seeds that i
really like and different flavors i
found this flavor combination to be my
favorite so what we actually have here
is an eighth a cup of pumpkin seeds of
course nice and high in zinc
we have an eighth cup of flax seeds
really nice and high in lignans and in
omega-3s
and then we have
an ate the cup of one of my all-time
favorites hemp seeds super nice
good uh
amino acid profile
just really really nutritious in general
so we're gonna put those in there
uh chris few questions on what kind of
nut milk bag are you using and if a nut
milk bag is easy to clean
you know the nut milk bag is pretty easy
to clean some people like to save the
fiber and use it for like crackers or
other things like that or even feed it
to animals and stuff like that
really all you have to do is just turn
it inside out and just tap it out and
then run it under some warm water it
takes maybe 30 seconds to a minute and
i really apologize i wish i knew the
exact name brand of this one that i have
because it is a good one it was given as
a gift and i i threw away the wrapper so
i apologize but i will look it up and
i'll ask to put it into the show notes
below
thanks you know what i use for a nut
milk bag is a paint strainer bag from
the hardware store for 99.
it's so much cheaper and they're so much
bigger so i can i can do a lot with it
yeah do big recipes then you know you
know in in a pinch i've used a a t-shirt
like a nice really clean t-shirt and
i've even used like a
non-synthetic non-dyed pantyhose which
works alright of course you don't want
to use used ones
you don't want to use it while the
person is still wearing it
no exactly unless maybe it's just for
you and you're making for yourself and
you don't care right but
it can get a little hazy there
so to this beautiful broth we'll add
about a pound of tomatoes and
you know i'm a big fan of tomatoes i
love tons of different varieties of
tomatoes and if you don't love tomatoes
i highly encourage you to try out some
different varieties maybe some heirloom
ones and especially home-grown ones
because the flavor from the store to
home
is so different and any recipe you make
that has tomatoes in it the quality of
the tomatoes is gonna make it you know
so i usually will go to my way to try
and get really good quality tomatoes
often the greenhouse-grown kind of
smaller camphori tomatoes or grape
tomatoes are even more flavorful and you
can really use any variety you want
these are just some typical canadian
greenhouse grown vine tomatoes and they
are quite good
so
i'm putting about a pound of those
tomatoes in there
let's see next what are we going to put
in there we'll put in the green onion so
i have three green onions you know
roughly about 50 grams and what i'm
going to do is i'm going to actually
just throw the bottom white part
right in the blender
the vitamix is so powerful it will just
chew it completely up
next i'm going to put in a thumb of
ginger i absolutely love ginger
nice anti-inflammatory properties and
high in different minerals so i just
throw the whole thing in there too this
is my laziness coming through
there is a lot of nutrition in the skin
and i opt usually for organic you just
put that in the whole thing in the
blender
and
i will do a little bit of garlic so one
clove of garlic some people like it some
people don't some people are afraid of
it because of the antibacterial or anti
antibiotic properties but it is really
interesting to note too that garlic as
well of onions have a fiber in them
known as aniline which is a prebiotic
fiber meaning it actually feeds certain
biotics in your microbiome so it can
help rebalance your microbiome so i like
garlic and occasion and it's really good
in this recipe being nice and authentic
so we're gonna put that in there
and then we're gonna go into spice town
now
the spices you put into this recipe will
really determine the major curry flavor
and i've made it with hundreds literally
hundreds over the last 10 years i've
been making curries um
of different types of curry powders and
every time it's different some of my
absolute favorites would be like uh
ethiopian berber or burberry it's like
one of my favorite curries ever or even
just like a madras curry you know
bombay curry there's so many different
types so you know this one here that i
have is just a really standard basic
kind of grocery store medium curry which
does pretty good but you can decide what
your favorite curry is and use it so
do you have a favorite curry by the way
um you know i love a company that's in
northern california called local spicery
i've had him on the show a few times his
name is nick devoran and his his spices
are just so good mostly organic
non-irradiated
small glass jars so i i love all of his
spices
that's awesome yeah i mean good spices
can totally make a dish and just change
like you could be eating the same thing
and use a different spice and it's a
totally different experience right
they they even have a spice called
pepperoni spice it's not real pepperoni
but it tastes like it
i gotta get my hands on that because i
tell you i know you mentioned it earlier
my freaking awesome freaking ross and
pizza book i do have raw vegan pepperoni
pizza in there that tastes pretty
legitimate like a pepperoni pizza and
one of the secret ingredients that my
girlfriend camilla actually tipped me
off to was a bit of fennel in there kind
of makes it like a slightly salami
pepperoni it's really good but i'd love
to try it with that spice so i'm gonna
have to ask you for that that address as
well
absolutely maybe he'd even send you some
if you if you promoted it on the show or
something like that you know yeah that'd
be cool always down to check out and
promote some different stuff that i
really would like you know does your
girlfriend eat like you
uh you know she's actually a raw food
chef and we met in bali
at a raw food culinary course
and you know she eats high raw but
doesn't eat all raw we were both in a
motorcycle accident two years ago and
actually almost died and during that
time of recovery she re-found her love
for toast and
and
so yeah we eat a lot of the same things
but she eats uh high raw vegan
nice
and she's an amazing stuff too so we
like to make food for each other what do
you like for instance what what does a
day's worth of eating look like for you
well you know i am a high fruit low-fat
raw foodist i'm not fat phobic so there
might be some days where i could have 20
to 30 fat in my diet but in general i'm
usually keeping it under 20 under 15
generally around the 80 10 10 guidelines
that dr douglas graham promotes in his
book the 80 10 10 diet which i love and
i'd say i think is one of the best books
if not the best book on raw food
nutrition out there so
that being said usually you know i've
been doing this 16 years so
when i first started i used to eat three
or four meals a day but over the years
it became bigger meals less often so
more often than not i'm actually only
eating two meals a day and um
if i'm eating two meals that might be
like a giant two-liter banana smoothie
for lunch and it might have some greens
in it i really love barley grass juice
powder
sometimes i like arugula in my banana
smoothie or spinach but it's a big
banana smoothie anywhere from 15 to 18
bananas and i feel great with that i'm
full for six hours and i'm really
charged up and then dinner
oftentimes i'll start it off with like
some orange juice or maybe even some
watermelon
depending on how active i am and then
i'll follow it up with something like a
curry or a big salad or
you know a wrap or anything like that
usually a savory dinner meal with a bit
of fat at the end of the day
and my salads are big they're big like
five pound salads
i love that you're doing savory
i love savory you know i eat more
vegetables than most people i know and
like usually i'm eating
at least two to five pounds of veggies a
day you know and um you know that's a
mix though like it might be a pound or
so of greens and it might be a pound of
broccoli or you know peas or it could be
cauliflower any of these different ones
i eat a lot of tomatoes you know they're
culinary-wise a vegetable but
botanically a fruit but i enjoy those a
lot and zucchinis and cucumbers but i
just think the greens and the veggies
are so important and that's one thing
that some raw food is going to get into
trouble with is not eating enough greens
and thinking just to eat fruits you know
so that's something i like to promote is
more vegetables and greens
yeah absolutely especially because not
everybody likes to eat sweet all the
time and most fruit well there are some
fruits that aren't sweet but a lot of
them are
absolutely yeah for sure and i mean it's
just a good balance and when we look out
to nature we look at the animals that
are the closest to us they don't just
eat fruit you know they eat a bunch of
greens and some of them actually eat way
more greens than fruit but the ones were
the closest to they do eat the most
fruit and they still eat a lot of greens
and
it's just delicious and tasty i mean
having a nice big crunchy salad you know
with a nice dressing or alone you know
it can be really delicious
yep
so let's let's get some of these spices
in here i will mention too
there are some optionals you know like
you could add some some lemon juice to
this to give it a little bit of an extra
zing if you do apple cider vinegar you
could add a tablespoon of that whatever
really you like to add a little bit of
extra flavor i like it like this and the
three base spices that i put in there
are usually curry powder so i'm gonna
put
one and a half tablespoons of curry
powder i like it to be nice and
flavorful
so
so i'm just putting about one and a half
in there
and then in canada we have chili powder
which isn't just you know like ground
chili's but instead it's a mix of like
cumin and pepper and garlic and paprika
a whole bunch of different spices which
i really love um oftentimes though when
i look in other countries for chili
powder it's just ground chili so if you
can't find a mixed chili powder i do
have on my website you can search it for
like a mixed recipe and you can make
your own i have here a chipotle chili
powder i absolutely love
you so i'm going to actually put a
tablespoon of chipotle chili powder
which is going to be very spicy i like
it spicy myself you can just use plain
chili powder if you like or
the other option that is really
delicious is smoked paprika
it's just a really nice flavor as well
and i'm actually going to double it up
because i want it nice and strong and
flavorful this will be my dinner today
so i'm going to put a tablespoon of that
in there as well so those are the main
spices that i'd say are kind of the base
if you want to take it up an extra notch
and add some different stuff in there
you can add
let's see about uh a quarter of a
teaspoon of mustard seeds which is kind
of traditional for east indian color and
culinary foods so i'm going to put that
in there i'm going to put in a
half of a no same quarter of a teaspoon
of cumin just for an extra punch
and turmeric which i absolutely love as
well so we're going to put a whole
teaspoon of turmeric
and you could otherwise just put a
little think pinky finger of fresh
turmeric and to really get that curcumin
in the turmeric which is the active
component that really helps with
inflammation and a whole bunch of other
processes we're also going to put just a
quarter teaspoon of black pepper that
really activates that
so we have all of those ingredients in
there
and all we have left to do is blend it
up
there are a few ingredients left but
we're going to leave them for the very
end so let's blend this up until
i forgot to turn it down first it's good
to turn it down for a certain
you know something neat with the vitamix
you know you can blend it till it boils
i'm not recommending that but if you
blend it for a little while it can get
nice and warm so if you want your curry
a little bit warmer you can just blend
it until it's a little bit steamy i'm
going to blend it until it's at least
really creamy so let's take another
probably 20 15 20 seconds
[Music]
this
there we go
i wish you guys could smell this
seriously it's like oh it's so rich and
creamy and just
deep curry smell so what we're going to
do then
is take a whole head
of cilantro i absolutely love cilantro
it's going to break it up
throw it in there this is an extra way
to get a ton more nutrition a lot of
extra greens you know herbs are some of
the actually they are the more nutrient
dense of the greens
per per calorie or per gram it's
unbelievable how thick you got it
because you really didn't use very much
fat you used like a quarter cup of seeds
uh i used uh let's see just shy of a
half a cup because three quarter cups so
i guess what is that uh
that's three fourths of a cup but still
i mean it's still it looks amazing it's
so thick
yeah or three six no three three-eighths
of a cup so that's just that's less than
a half a cup that's yes less than a half
a cup and you know i mean the spices
themselves they thicken it up as well
and i mean if you want you could add
sun-dried tomatoes or you could add
you know something like that to thicken
up as well but the quantities given it
makes a really nice thick and creamy
curry with a really good balance of fats
in there and yeah not too high but it's
enough to give some extra calories a lot
of nutrition right
so
with these guys here
this is where i like to use the tamper
as well because i don't want to just
pulverize the greens and i also snuck in
the green onion tops just in case you
missed it so it's the whole head of
cilantro and the three green onion
greens and i'm just gonna put this down
at about about a four and a half or five
on the vitamix turn it on and just use
the tamper
get it all in there
and give it a pulse or two
that way it saves me from chopping and
chopping and chopping and chopping
the lazy theme is really coming out
today sorry about that
so
there we go
and
it's very good
very good so chris we have a couple of
cilantro haters on and wanted to know if
they could substitute maybe italian
parsley
you know you absolutely could or you
could do basil or basil however you like
to pronounce it or you don't even need
it at all you know it's totally fine
without the herb
it is interesting with cilantro it's a
genetic disposition it's a specific gene
turned on or off if you love cilantro
then it's either on or off if you hate
it it's on or off this other one so it's
not something to force yourself i've met
some people like i hate it but i'm
forcing myself to like it
it's not worth it you know just enjoy
what you enjoy
so here we have it are we ready for it
to pour on you bet
look at that look how thick and creamy
that sauce is oh my gosh
sometimes i do this and then i pour the
whole thing into a pyrex dish and i put
the whole thing in my dehydrator and
just warm it up a little bit
but we're just going to have this
perfectly as is
stir this up
and this recipe might be going holy cow
that's big you know this serves between
one to four people you know like for
myself this is a perfect serving just
for me
but for a lot of people you know if it's
a side dish it might serve up to four or
five people really but again if you're
just starting if you don't normally eat
a lot of raw cauliflower or mushrooms
this might be two or three portions it
does keep for the next day or two at the
most and otherwise you can make it for a
bunch of friends
that looks so good and you know you
didn't have to use oil or salt or
anything bad nothing at all like that at
all just all whole foods a little bit of
spices and
it's really rich it's really creamy it's
really savory and i tell you this is one
of those cravings buster satisfying
dishes that leaves you feeling like i
don't even eat cooked food in my life if
you have something like this it's pretty
easy
wow
you are talented i can tell i would love
to taste your food i would eat that
oh well i hope that i get the chance to
serve you some food whether it be
something like this or shepherd's pies
or pizzas and shamelessly i'll let
everyone know i do have a free app with
over 100 recipes on it it's called the
raw advantage raw recipes on android and
on apple
and i got tons more at rawadvantage.com
but i just love sharing this food just
like you you know you it's made such a
difference in my life that i can't help
but want to share it and help other
people improve their life
so what are you doing now because we i
mean what's it like up in canada with
the pandemic you probably can't travel
too much i would imagine
you know i'm i'm actually in quarantine
right now because i just got back from
sweden where i'm actually migrating to
live full-time with my girlfriend
camilla
and so i'm back here with my family and
you know i really love it here i grew up
here and got the kitties and my parents
and the whole family and all i've been
doing is behind the scenes work i'm
doing a lot of behind the scenes work on
theradvantage.com
uh to bring people more more recipes and
easier easier functionality to get them
into their life so that's kind of what
i'm doing you know otherwise i have an
online course
uh raw vegan lifestyle success system
which teaches a whole holistic kind of
point of view for the raw food lifestyle
to help people find more ease in it
because like you said it can be kind of
challenging for a lot of people right so
i like to try and make it easier um
they're asking if you could come a
little closer to the camera and hold the
dish so they can see it and take a
picture absolutely
that looks so good i want a picture i
want that to be the uh the thumbnail
that's amazing so monica says what is
the name of the app
so the app is called the raw advantage
raw recipes you put that in there it'll
pop right up um and again it is free
with over 100 recipes there's tons of
videos in there and then there also are
in-app purchases to unlock my entire
recipe books because i have actually
eight recipe books i believe six of
which are seven of which are on there so
it can have up to like 370 recipes i
think on the app if you unlock the rest
books but
like i said the the base functionality
and 100 recipes are free on it
nice and teresa says how's your mom
oh my mom's doing great yeah she's doing
good so maybe camilla would like to be
on the show sometime
that'd be awesome yeah i bet you she
would absolutely i'll be back and i'll
be back in sweden uh if all goes well in
january and it sounds like you're booked
up until march anyway hey oh but you
know sometimes i get cancellations so
you know let me know what do you do in
sweden
you know i mean everything i do is
online right so i do the recipe books i
do retreats which i'm i'm usually
holding costa rica but i'm taking a year
off with everything going on in the
world
and otherwise i do online consultations
and my success system so wherever i am
i'm working online just doing the same
thing spreading tasty food and helping
people with you know the logistics and
emotional kind of aspects of applying a
raw food lifestyle yeah well you seem
like a great guy you're nice and chill
you seem very non-judgmental
well i i'd like to be i mean i don't
like to be judged myself you know so i i
really do try and apply the golden rule
in my life and just everyone's my friend
you know that's the way i look at it
honestly every single person's my friend
maybe they don't think that they're my
friend but you know i'm going to treat
everyone the same and do my absolute
best to love everyone equally well lori
says you have amazing cinnamon buns
they are darn tasty i tell ya yeah they
definitely are
wow and just so people know too
excalibur's are on sale right now you
know 20 off with the code harvest 20 i
think so if you like to make dehydrated
food that's not even my affiliate link
but you can just go to excalibur and get
20 off right now all right
diane wants to know what your cats are
named it's so cute how your cats just
come and go
yeah they're the absolute best uh
they're sisters and one is named dottie
and the other one's name is dede
they're adorable
they are serious cuddle monsters all
they want to do is just cuddle you and
purr and you you call them they'll come
they're
they're seriously amazing cats like
super cats you know what i wonder like
in the in the vegan i've been vegan for
over 43 years and there's all different
kinds of vegans people go vegan for
different reasons their health the
environment the animals the combination
and there's vegans that are junk food
vegans which is what which i'm not
saying is a bad thing i was one of those
for 26 years and they're vegans that
don't eat oil and there's vegans that
don't eat sugar and vegans that don't
eat oil sugar and you know there's all
different kinds of vegans right and but
it seems like with raw food it's it's
that's that's the same way too you're 80
10 10 like robbie barbaro and some of
the others but other rough fooders eat
things that are different they might eat
a lot of oil and salt and agave and
do do do you guys get along did those
two groups get along or do they fight
the way that the vegans fight within
amongst each other you know i i think
within any group there's people that
fight amongst each other you know like
like i said i love everyone and if
people really want to talk shop well of
course i'll share my opinion and my
experience and my learning but
that's secondary you know like to me
it's like you know we're all in the same
team you know no matter what we're
eating we're all on the same team uh and
so i like to try and bridge the gap and
to be friends with everyone and you know
i have friends that eat all different
types of things right i still have
friends that drink and smoke and do
drugs all the time right and i don't try
and treat them any different just trying
to be the example and have real
conversations you know that's uh that's
what i'm about right because the one
thing i never understood in the in the
more gourmet raw food world is that so
i've known some raw foodists who like
literally will not eat a piece of
steamed broccoli but they'll pour tons
of olive oil on their food and how can
they
you know the way doug graham teaches it
it makes health sense you know what i'm
saying
absolutely and you know that's what it
comes down to too is why is the person
doing it and some people they're raw
foods to be raw foodists
and maybe
they subscribe to certain information or
philosophy that isn't really updated and
true when it kind of comes to scientific
backgrounds right so i mean that's i
think where it kind of comes into it is
if someone has a bit of a science mind
or if they're just purely on a
philosophical kind of stance or
otherwise right and i totally agree i
would rather have some very lightly
steamed vegetables or steamed vegetables
than have a jar of nut butter just to
say i'm still raw you know so
i i think that you know if you're
specifically eating raw for health then
there might be a little bit more leeway
because you know truthfully stress comes
into it too and transition comes into it
too and if you're just stressing
yourself out you could be doing yourself
more harm staying away from a couple
pieces of steamed broccoli then forcing
yourself to stay 100 raw
right
may we ask your age diane is that
inquiring
yeah yeah i'm 40 years old uh just this
past summer oh my god you look half
oh thank you that's kind of yeah if
hopefully this isn't uh 4k because then
you might see some of the wrinkles
although i got scars right on the
wrinkle zones it's not fun i i found
your app and i'm getting it right now
thank you yeah thank you for letting me
know about it well you've been a great
guest and a lot of fun and your food
looks delicious so i'd love to have you
back sometime maybe
with your girlfriend or she could do her
own episode
i would absolutely love that i'd love to
be back on myself with my girlfriend and
her by herself as well i'll say 100 i'd
love that well we love cooking them was
and i'm going to definitely try this
recipe because it looked amazing well
thank you so much chris and everybody
check the show notes we'll have
everything in them pretty soon crystal
send me all the links to his nut milk
bag and all of his books and his
retreats and whatever else he's up to
make the recipe and also come back
tomorrow when i have a story of recovery
from somebody who had two heart attacks
and is now completely plant-based and
sharing the message his name is doug
schmidt thanks again chris so nice to
have you on the show thank you so much
chef aj and everyone here bye